A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977
Virginia Historical Society
Virginia Historical Society
A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977
Virginia Historical Society
Mss1 W6326 c FA2
11,500 (ca.) items (51 manuscript boxes).
The collection includes correspondence (some copies), 1778-1799, of attorney John Wickham (1763-1839) of Richmond, Va., and extensive materials concerning the settlement of his estate (including wills, correspondence, financial, land and legal records, and trust materials, some involving Robert E. Lee and William Henry Fitzhugh Lee). Also contains papers of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) of "Hickory Hill," Hanover County, Va., including diaries (17 v.), 1828-1880, concerning agricultural operations, slave families and runaway slaves, and local events during the Civil War and Reconstruction; family correspondence, 1817-1878; accounts; land records; and materials concerning the emancipation and resettlement in Ohio of slaves belonging to the estate of Samuel Gist. Also contains letterbooks, 1877-1881, of Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888) as a Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company official and Republican Party State Executive Committee chairman; correspondence, 1862-1888; financial records; "Hickory Hill" farm records; and materials concerning the management of "North Wales," Caroline County, Va., for Dr. Charles Carter of Philadelphia, Pa. Alsoincludes correspondence, 1848-1913, financial records, and estate materials of Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham (1830-1913); letterbooks, 1931-1940, scrapbooks, correspondence, 1874-1941, farm records, and Virginia Senate and Democratic Party materials of Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943) of "Hickory Hill"; correspondence, accounts, farm records, and Richmond, Va., rental property records of Elise Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham; and miscellaneous records of other members of the Wickham and Fanning families.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Credilla B. W. Bordley, Ashland, Va., and Lawrence V. M. Wickham, Hanover, Va., in 1987. Accessioned 22 July 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Wickham family of Richmond and Hanover County, known as the "Hickory Hill Wickhams," was founded by the celebrated post-Revolutionary attorney John Wickham (1763-1839). This collection traces the descendants of Wickham and his first wife, Mary Smith Fanning, through the line of his eldest son, William Fanning Wickham.
Scope and Content Information
The collection opens with materials of William Fanning (1728-1782) of Brunswick and Greensville counties, Va., an Anglican clergyman who was both an uncle of John Wickham and father of Wickham's first wife. Included are a certificate of ordination, 1754, issued to Fanning as a deacon in the Church of England (signed by the Bishop of Gloucester and bearing a seal of the Bishop of London); a 1781 letter of Fanning to Virginia Governor Thomas Nelson (a copy made in 1857) concerning John Wickham; and a will probated in Greensville County. Early folders also contain notes on the Fanning, Gray, Tazewell, and Wickham families (apparently taken from the family Bible of Mary (Gray) Tazewell Fanning); and correspondence, 1930, of Henry Taylor Wickham with George MacLaren Brydon concerning William and Edmund Fanning.
Series 2 contains papers of Edmund Fanning (1739-1818), another of Wickham's uncles who took a particular interest in the younger man's education and career. Edmund Fanning pursued his own colorful career in colonial administration and eventually served as governor of Nova Scotia. His records in this collection include correspondence, 1738-ca. 1812, with Sir Robert Pigot, John Wickham (concerning Wickham's service in the King's American Regiment and as a lawyer in Richmond, Va.), and Mary Smith (Fanning) Wickham; letters, 1777-1778 (copies made in 1873) of Fanning (while serving in the King's American Regiment) to James Fanning and Hannah Smith (Fanning) Wickham (concerning John Wickham); a prayer, ca. 1788, for the governor, council, and assembly of Prince Edward Island, Canada; and biographical sketches, ca. 1800-1829.
Series 3 contains a limited number of John Wickham's own personal records survive in Box 1 of this collection. Letters, 1806, written to Philadelphia merchant David Parish concern the personal and financial affairs of entrepreneur David Ross; while letters, 1778-1799 (copies of which were made in 1873-1874) written to John Wickham (1734-1808) and Harriet Smith (Fanning) Wickham, John Wickham's parents, describe his travels in Europe and practice of law in Richmond, Va.
John Wickham's land records, 1801-1842, primarily concern plantations in Henrico and Goochland counties known as "Middle Quarter," "Lower Quarter," and "Ellerslie" and are related to his acquisition of the "East Tuckahoe" plantation. These papers consist of proceedings, exhibits, decrees, and other records from the lawsuit of Wakelyn Welch, surviving partner of Robert Cary and Company of London v. the executors of Thomas Mann Randolph (a British debt case that concerns in part the sale of "Middle Quarter Plantation" and its Negro slaves to Wickham in 1800) signed by George Wythe and bearing a seal of the Virginia High Court of Chancery; a deed of trust, 1838, of Wickham to BenjaminWatkins Leigh and William Fanning Wickham for the benefit of John Wickham's children (deed covers slaves, cattle, horses, and personal property on the plantation); and a newspaper notice, 1842, of the public auction of these lands.
Wickham's miscellany contains a commission, 1782, in the King's American Regiment of Foot (signed by George III and Thomas Townshend, Viscount Sydney, and bears seal); an argument, 1795, of John Wickham (through not in his hand) as counsel for the U.S. in the U.S. Circuit Court at Richmond in U.S. v. Daniel Lawrence Hylton (concerning the constitutionality of the federal carriage tax); a deed of trust (copy), 1800 to shares in the Bank of Baltimore for the benefit of Mary (Gray) Tazewell Fanning; a statement, ca. 1820, of the case of John Ponsonby Martin concerning the confiscation of the Virginia estate of John Martin by the Commonwealth of Virginia in 1779; a student notebook, n.d., used (probably by one of Wickham's children) to practice handwriting; lines of verse, 1835, copied from the Southern Literary Messenger concerning Wickham's speech before the Virginia House of Delegates; and drafts of a biographical sketch, 1887, by Williams Carter Wickham.
The next three boxes (Boxes 2-4) cover the very extensive and complicated proceedings over the estate of John Wickham. Due to a number of technicalities, Wickham's estate matters eventually absorbed the estates of Richmond physician James McClurg, his father-in-law, and of several of his children who died young, and gave rise to an enormous amount of litigation.
The estate records begin with two copies of Wickham's lengthy will, 1839, probated in Richmond. Correspondence, 1852-1875, of William Fanning Wickham (as surviving executor with Benjamin Watkins Leigh) including numerous letters from Julia (Wickham) Leigh (concerning family affairs and the U.S. Customs House in Richmond), John Wickham (1825-1892) of St. Louis, Mo., and John Wickham (1825-1902) of "East Tuckahoe," Henrico County, Va. An account book, 1856-1880, kept by William Fanning Wickham bears frequent notes on transactions and financial affairs of the estate and on his trusteeship for a younger Wickham daughter, Frances (Wickham) Graham. Loose accounts cover the period 1848-1863; bonds, 1853-1869. Materials concerning land of John Wickham in Kentucky and Missouri and of Doctor McClurg in Randolph County [W.Va.] and in Kentucky (Folder 5) include correspondence with Joseph Rogers Underwood and others and notes of William Fanning Wickham. Estate miscellany consists of a petition to and order of the Richmond Circuit Court in 1864; materials, 1858, concerning Amy (a Negro slave) at Eastern Lunatic Asylum (later Eastern State Hospital) in Williamsburg, Va., and notes of William Fanning Wickham.Box 4 contains records of a trust established by the estate for a granddaughter of John Wickham, Charlotte Georgiana Wickham, upon her marriage in 1859 to William Henry Fitzhugh Lee. William Fanning Wickham and Robert E. Lee served as trustees. Materials include the deed of trust (marriage settlement) establishing the trust, signed by all the above parties plus Williams Carter (grandfather of the bride and her guardian); notes and memoranda of William Fanning Wickham, 1858-1868; and an order and receipt, 1866-1868, of William Henry Fitzhugh Lee concerning shares of Virginia 6% state stock (also signed by Robert E. Lee).
Correspondence of William Fanning Wickham as trustee includes numerous communications with Doctor Charles Carter, Robert E. Lee, and William Henry Fitzhugh Lee (of "Arlington," "Ravensworth," Fairfax County, and "White House," New Kent County). Two bank books and some loose accounts cover the period 1854-1867. Materials, 1856-1879, concern lot #502 at Grace and Sixth streets in Richmond and #533 at Broad and Sixth streets, owned respectively by Maclurg Wickham and W. H. F. Lee in the division of the estate of Doctor James McClurg. Another group of records, 1861, concern the lot and tenanment on Cary Street adjoining the Bank of Richmond, A deed of release (copy), 1867, of W. H. F. Lee conveys land in Warwick County, Va., received from the estate of Doctor William Foushee. Lastly, materials, 1880-1882, concern a lawsuit in Richmond Chancery Court of William Henry Fitzhugh Lee v. William Carter Wickham (executor of William Fanning Wickham) etal. (including correspondence of Wickham and Lee, an answer of Wickham, exhibits, receipts, and notes).
Series 4, containing the personal records of William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880) commences with Box 5. A prominent attorney of early Richmond like his father, William Fanning Wickham retired early to his plantation in Hanover County, "Hickory Hill," and devoted the rest of his life to his family and to agriculture. He kept a long series of diaries (17 volumes) beginning in 1828, in which he recorded little of a personal nature but much on agricultural operations. weather, the sale of produce, plantation life, horse breeding, and local affairs. Many of the diaries include lists of Negro slaves (with their ages) at"Hickory Hill" and adjoining plantations, as well as records of slave births and deaths. Some volumes include plats of fields (beginning with volume 5). Volume 8 covers the Hanover County homefront during the Civil War, describing the treatment of slaves and noting runaways to the Union Army. It mentions a battle near "Hickory Hill" on 27 May 1862 (entry for 31 May), news of campaigns and Union raids during the summers of 1862 and 1863, and reports on the Spotsylvania Campaign, 14-31 May 1864. Volume XIV reports the devastating fire at "Hickory Hill" on 13 February 1875.Wickham's general correspondence covers the period 1817-1878 and is generally maintained with family members. Letters to Anne Butler (Carter) Wickham and William Carter Wickham mostly concern the elder Wickham's trip to Europe in 1852 (visiting Geneva, London, Paris, and Rome). Other correspondents include Doctor Charles Carter of Philadelphia (largely concerning the estate of Williams Carter, and "North Wales," in Caroline County, letters dated 1865 concern the postwar crisis in Virginia), Edmund Fontaine (concerning train stops on the Virginia Central Railroad in Hanover County), William Cabell Rives, Judith Page (Walker) Rives (concerning the death of William Cabell Rives), Littleton Waller Tazewell (imperfect), James Maclurg Wikcham (concerning the death of George Wickham) and Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham. Letters of condolence, sent to William Fanning Wickham upon the death of Anne Butler (Carter) Wickham in 1868, also include acknowledgements by Wickham (especially to Robert E. Lee) and other members of the Carter and Wickham families, and a prayer by Wickham.
Wickham's financial records in Box 7 include accounts, 1828-1841, 1854-1863, and 1872-1878; a memoranda book of stocks, 1853-1861; bonds, 1878, of Wickham to John Henry Wickham and Mrs. Maria F. Wickham; and bonds, 1879, with E. and S. Wortham, Richmond commission merchants.
"Hickory Hill" land records cover the acquisition of the plantation and adjoining acreage between 1828 and 1878 which totaled nearly 3500 acres by the latter date. An 1878 survey report, title history, and map give an overview of the gradual evolution of the plantation. Folder 1 contains deeds, 1820-1828, of the heirs of George William Smith to William Fanning Wickham and include an agreement, power of attorney, and plat. A deed, plat, and survey cover the lands of Doctor Josiah Holt. Other records consist of deeds, agreements, and plants, 1836-1837, of adjacent lands acquired from the heirs of John D. Thilman; plats, notes, and a deed covering the John H. Taliaferro lands, 1837-1858; a deed and plats, 1867-1873, of land exchanged with Edmund Winston; plats and surveys of "Hickory Hill," ca. 1852-1861; miscellaneous adjacent tracts, 1833-1867; notes of William Fanning Wickham; and a deed, 1880, of Wickham to Williams Carter Wickham.
Folder 2 consists of a report, 1844, concerning a petition to build a mill dam t power grist and saw mills; estimated values and lists of taxable real and personal property, 1823, 1852-1864, 1873; records, 1842-1857, concerning the purchase of slaves; accounts of expenses of farm operations, 1866-1876; and records of the division of the farm into a field system for crop rotation, 1871-1878. The next folder concerns "South Wales," the largest trace of the "Hickory Hill" plantation. Materialsinclude a letter, 1769, of Harry Terrill concerning farming operations; a plat, n.d., of a portion of the tract between the railroad and the county road; agreements, 1859, with the Virginia Central Railroad Company; and a survey and plat, n.d., of the Hanover Courthouse Road. Lastly, Folder 4 concerns "The Lane" (a tract also known as "Lanefield" or "Long Lane"). Items include a deed, 1825, of Thomas Nelson Carter, deed of trust, agreement, and bond; a bond, 1841, of Elizabeth Jacquelin (Ambler) Brent Carrington (with deeds of trust and release); a bond, 1843, of Wickham to Littleton Waller Tazewell (with deeds of trust and release); and undated plats.
One of the most interesting matters handled by William Fanning Wickham as an attorney concerned the estate of Samuel Gist (d. 1815), a London merchant. Gist lived in Virginia for a number of years but returned to England before the American Revolution. During that conflict, the Commonwealth of Virginia sought to confiscate his lands and goods but the General Assembly was prevailed upon to enact legislation in 1782 vesting his property in the hands of a daughter Mary (Gist) Anderson Pearkes and her first husband, William Anderson. Gist continued to receive the profits from his estates after the war through his manager in Hanover County, Benjamin Toler, and by his will sought to emancipate his slaves and provide for their welfare through the sale of property in Goochland County. An act of Assembly in 1816 created a trust supervised by the Superior Court of Chancery in Richmond to be administered until all creditors of the estate were satisfied, when funds could be generated from the sale of land and other property to benefit the freed slaves, who in turn had to leave the Commonwealth. William Fanning Wickham acted as one of the trustees from 1817 until 1847 and in 1858-1859 heard from members of the Quaker committee devoted to the care of free blacks in Ohio, where Gist's slaves finally settled. The whole issue was raised again in 1877-1880 by E. Cumberland, one of the original freedmen who moved to Ohio and settled on lands purchased through funds from the estate but which the blacks had no right to alienate themselves.
Materials from the Gist estate include correspondence of William Fanning Wickham as surviving trustee with agents, attorneys, former slaves, and Quakers in Ohio (especially David Bailey, a former resident of Petersburg, and George Carter) during three periods: 1845-1849 (closing the Virginia affairs of the trust), 1850-1858 (reports from Ohio Friends), and 1870-1880 (the re-establishment of extended claims by former Gist slaves and their descendants). General materials include loose accounts, 1826-1853; bonds, 1819; records, 1832-1847, concerning the acquisition of lands in Brown and Highland counties, Ohio, and the maintenance of former slaves; and a letter (copy) of John Wickham (1763-1839) to John Hampden Pleasants concerning his role as one of the original trustees.
Records from supervision of the Gist estate by the Virginia Superior Court of Chancery in Richmond (later the Circuit Superior Court of Chancery) include memorials to the court, decrees, orders, etc., 1845- 1847, and a long series of commissioner's reports, 1818-1847. Records of the case Archibald Anderson etal. v. Samuel Gist's executors etal., heard by Chief Justice John Marshall in the Fifth U.S. Circuit Court for the Virginia District in Richmond (concerning claims under the will of William Anderson) consist of an 1824 decree of the court, a statement of accounts, notes of argument of the opposing counsel (Robert Stanard and Benjamin Watkins Leigh), and agreement and bond with Richard Anderson, and miscellany (copy of an amended bill of complaint and letter of William Fanning Wickham to Chancellor Creed Taylor).
William Fanning Wickham also served for many years as agent or trustee for his younger sister Frances (Wickham) Graham after the death of her husband. Records include an account book, 1867=1880; loose accounts, 1871-1882; bonds, 1875-1879, of John Wickham (1825-1902), Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham, and Maclurg Wickham; agreements, 1874-1878, concerning cash advances for her above-named brothers; a lease, 1868, to Grubbs and Williams of Richmond to a lot on Eleventh Street between Main and Bank streets; and a receipt, 1881, for payment for buildings erected on that lot. Specific materials concerning the indebtedness of John and Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham to Maclurg Wickham are comprised of deeds of trust, 1858-1877, to "East Tuckahoe" and "Woodside," Henrico County; a deed of trust (copy) concerning mineral rights, 1874, granted to the James River Coal Company; a plat of "East Tuckahoe," ca. 1858; and materials of William Fanning Wickham concerning John Wickham's bankruptcy proceedings.
Additional personal records of William Fanning Wickham (Boxes 9-10) include pardon materials, 1865 (provost marshal's certificate, petition to President Andrew Johnston, certificate of the Secretary of State (William Henry Seward), and pardon document); notes, charts, and materials collected by Wickham concerning the Carter, Fanning, Nelson, Randolph and Wickham families (see also general correspondence); and a commonplace book, n.d. (early nineteenth century), consisting primarily of descriptive and historical notes on England and English counties.
Wickham's miscellany includes a sketch of Benjamin Watkins Leigh prepared by William Hamilton Macfarland; a personal reminiscence of John Marshall; a commonplace bok, n.d. consisting of notes on the U.S. Constitution and constitutional history; essay speech, n.d., probably made at Hanover Court House concerning reconstruction in Virginia; an inventory of personal papers; a letter, 1843, of Thomas Tabb Giles to William Daniel (concerning a book in the library at "Hickory Hill"); lines of verse; and miscellaneous notes. Estate materials consist of a will probated in Hanover County, accounts, a letter to the executor (Williams Carter Wickham), and bonds.
Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), a son of William Fanning Wickham, trained as a lawyer but abandoned the law early to become a planter at "Hickory Hill." He served as a local militia officer prior to the Civil War and became a cavalry general in the army of Northern Virginia. After the war, he surprised neighbors and fellow veterans by joining the Republican party, a political organization in which he became very influential. For many years a second vice-president of the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company, Wickham also served in the Virginia Senate, where he opposed the Readjusters. His materials are represented in Series 5.
An important group of three postwar letterbooks (letter-press) kept by Williams Carter Wickham survives in this collection. Volume I covers the years 1877 to 1880 and is largely devoted to personal and business affairs and Republican party politics. (Indexes to each of the letterbooks have been prepared by VHS staff members and are filed with the appropriate volumes.) Among the individuals to whom Wickham addresses letters in this volume are Robert Rufus Bridgers, Doctor Charles Carter (of Philadelphia, concerning the estate of Williams Carter and "North Wales," Caroline County, VA), John Echols, Charles Meriwether Fry (concerning the Chesapeake Coal Company of New York), President Rutherford B. Hayes, Virginia Governor Frederick William Mackey Holliday, Collis Potter Huntington, Hugh McCullock, William Snead Oakey (of Salem, Va.), Doctor Thomas Pollard (concerning the use of marl at "Hickory Hill"), John Warren Porter (of the Charlottesville Republican), George William Richardson (concerning the sale of "Oakland," Hanover County, Va.), William Lawrence Royall, James Beverley Sener, U. S. Treasury secretary John Sherman, Samuel M. Yost (a Republican party associate), Haxall-Crenshaw Company of Richmond, and the Richmond Whig.
Letterbook II (1880-1881) also concerns Wickham's personal and business affairs, some relating to the C. and O. Railroad, plantation operations and agricultural production, Republican party activities, and St. Paul's Church in Hanover County (see especially letters to Bickerton Lyle Winston). Among the addressees are Chester A. Arthur, James G. Blaine, Doctor Charles Carter, Robert Randolph Carter, John Callaghan (of Norfolk), Charles Meriwether Fry, Philip Haxall (as president of Haxall-Crenshaw Company, Richmond), Collis Potter Huntington (concerning William Lawrence Royall [p. 7] and artist John Adams Elder [p.2651], William Henry Fitzhugh Lee, Conway Robinson (concerning the trial of Aaron Burr, a dinner for Burr hosted by John Wickham and attended by Chief Justice John Marshall, and Benjamin Watkins Leigh), George William Richardson, James Beverley Sener, Henry Taylor, and Samuel M. Yost.
Finally, Volume III (also 1880-1881) was kept as chairman of the Republican State Executive Committee, concerns activities of the Central Committee and the Republican State Convention in Lynchburg in August 1881, and includes letters written to Republican leaders throughout Virginia, especially concerning the presidential election of 1880 and state elections in 1881. Among the addressees are John Callaghan, President James A. Garfield, Doctor Joseph Jorgenson, John Singleton Mosby, Arthur Alexander Spitzer, J. B. Work, and Samuel M. Yost.